Guide to the Missoula Electric Cooperative Records 1950-1979
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Missoula Electric Cooperative Records
1950-1979
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 229
Missoula Electric Cooperative
5.5 linear feet
The Missoula Electric Cooperative was formed in 1936 to supply power in and around Missoula, Montana. The collection includes general information about MEC including correspondence, history, and technical and financial reports.
Historical Note
The 1935 Montana legislature passed the State Electrification Authority Act, which tied Montana into contact with the state water development projects. In the same year, President Roosevelt formed the Rural Electric Administration in the U.S. Department of Agriculture. Missoula Electric Cooperative, Inc., (MEC) was formed in Missoula, Montana, in 1936. It was one of several electric co-operatives formed because the Montana Power Company, the state's major provider, would not provide power in many rural areas because construction costs outweighed potential profits. Members of the co-op paid a fee, installation and consumption costs; the organization is non-profit. Electric cooperatives played an important role in rural electrification in Montana and many other states. Eugene Pike came to work for the co-op in 1937. Soon after it was formed, the MEC received a loan from the Rural Electrification Administration to build power lines from Missoula to Frenchtown, down the Bitterroot Valley, and out to Clinton, a project known as the "A" project. When World War II began, power line construction slowed considerably, and the company stopped construction in 1943. Pike returned from his shipyard job to become co-op manager in 1946.
There was no power supplier for Seeley Lake, Montana, at this time, and the co-op wished to begin line construction. They were unable to get a loan for this from the REA because the co-op purchased its power from Montana Power, and the rates they were being charged were too high. However, the REA agreed to lend the co-op the money for line construction if they bought their power from another supplier at a lower rate. Bonneville Power wished to do business in Montana, but the Montana Power Company did not welcome this competition. Senator James Murray helped pass legislation to allow Bonneville Power to come into Montana so that the co-op would be able to build its line to Seely Lake. The co-op remained hooked up to Montana Power lines, but would pay Bonneville Power for the electricity; Bonneville in turn paid Montana Power. The co-op also explored other power sources, including the fledgling nuclear power industry.
The co-op constantly clashed with the Montana Power Company over questions of competition in the state. In the late 1960s, the MEC clashed with Montana Power Company over territorial integrity, the question of whether the for-profit companies could begin to serve customers in territories formerly served only by the co-ops. The state legislature finally resolved some of these conflicts in 1970.
The collection contains information from 1957-1975. Most of the information was written by or sent to Eugene Pike. There is general information about MEC including correspondence, history, and technical and financial reports. The collection includes numerous training manuals from the Rural Electric Administration. There is information about co-operative utilities in Montana, the Pacific Northwest and the United States. There is detailed information regarding power generation in the northwest including nuclear, hydroelectric and hydrothermal.
The collection is divided into nineteen series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1.0 linear foot, 1956-1977
Series II: Clippings, 4 folders, 1953-1976
Series III: Certificates, 1 folder, 1966-1969
Series IV: Publications, 2 folders, 1960-1969
Series V: Speeches and Writings, 1 folder, 1958-1973
Series VI: Legislation, 0.25 linear feet, 1961-1976
Series VII: National Rural Electric Co-Op Association, 0.5 linear feet, 1960-1976
Series VIII: U. S. Department of Agriculture, Rural Electric Administration, 1 folder, 1951-1959
Series IX: Montana Associated Utilities, 4 folders, 1962-1976
Series X: Bonneville Power Company, 0.25 linear feet, 1963-1976
Series XI: Breeder Reactor Corporation, 0.25 linear feet, 1971-1976
Series XII: Northwest Intertie, 0.25 linear feet, 1963-1975
Series XIII: Washington Public Power Supply System, 1.0 linear foot, 1962-1977
Series XIV: Public Power Council, 0.5 linar feet, 1966-1976
Series XV: Federal Power Commission, 2 folders,1963 and 1975
Series XVI: Northwest Public Power Association, 5 folders, 1968-1976
Series XVII: Montana Power Company, 2 folders, 1957-1966
Series XIX: Other Groups, 0.5 linear feet, 1962-1979
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Held by the Missoula Electric Cooperative until donation.
Gift of Missoula Electric Cooperative, 1977 and 1978.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Pike, Eugene
United States. Bonneville Power Administration; United States. Federal Power Commission; Breeder Reactor Corporation; Montana Associated Utilities; Montana Electric Cooperatives' Association; Montana Power Company; National Rural Electric Cooperative Association; Northwest Public Power Association; United States. Rural Electrification Administration
Consumer cooperatives--Montana; Consumer cooperatives--Montana--Missoula; Electric power--Montana; Electric power--Northwest, Pacific; Hydroelectric power plants--Northwest, Pacific; Hydrothermal electric power systems; Nuclear power plants--Northwest, Pacific; Rural electrification--Montana
Montana; Labor History
- Correspondence, 1956-1977; Series I; 1.0 linear foot
  Consists of correspondence between the MEC and other electric administration entities, including the Bonneville Power Administration, Rural Electric Administration, and other co-ops.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with two folders of general correspondence at the beginning of the sequence.
  - General, 1956-1969 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, all customers, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1970 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1971 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1972 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1973 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1974 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1975 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Bonneville Power Administration, general, 1976 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Federal Power Commission, 1965 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Institute of Ecology, 1974 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Montana Associated Utilities, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Montana Power, 1965-1975 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - National Rural Electric Cooperative Association, 1963-1971 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Northwest Intertie, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Northwest Public Power Association, 1958-1977 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Northwest Public Power Association, Pacific Northwest Utilities Conference Committee, 1976 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Public Power Council, 1970 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Public Power Council, 1971 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Public Power Council, 1972 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Public Power Council, 1973 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Public Power Council, 1974 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Public Power Council, 1975 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Public Power Council, special memoranda, 1975 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Public Power Council, 1976 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - U.S. Department of Agriculture, Rural Electrification Administration, 1952-1973 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Clippings, 1953-1976; Series II; 4 folders
  This series is composed of newspaper and magazine clippings collected by the MEC. Most concern territorial integrity and other matters specific to Montana.
  Arranged chronologically, with two separate folders for clippings about Paradise Dam and territorial integrity.
  - 1953-1976 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - 1961-1975 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Paradise Dam, undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Territorial Integrity, 1971 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Certificates, 1966-1969; Series III; 1 folder
  Consists of three certificates presented to the MEC from civic entities in Missoula like the Missoula County Fair Association.
  - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 3/5)
- Publications, 1960-1969; Series IV; 2 folders
  This series contains MEC rate schedules and copies of the company's report, A Look to the Past and a Plan for the Future.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - A Look at the Past and Plan for the Future, 1966 and 1969 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Rate schedules, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 3/7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1958-1973; Series V; 1 folder
  Composed of statements of Eugene Pike, mostly before the Montana state legislature on territorial integrity.
  - Statements of Eugene Pike, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 3/8)
- Legislation, 1961-1976; Series VI; 0.25 linear feet
  This series represents the MEC's involvement with state and federal legislation governing electric generation and delivery. It includes information on the MEC's lobby for Paradise Dam and numerous folders of materials on territorial integrity.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General, 1965-1976 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Federal legislation, s. 3362, 1974 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Paradise Dam, 1957-1965 and undated (Box-folder 3/11)
  - State Electrification Authority Act, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
  - State legislation, 1968-1974 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - State: House legislation, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - State: Senate legislation, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Territorial integrity, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Territorial integrity, correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Territorial integrity bills, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Territorial integrity: House Bill #5, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Territorial integrity: House Bill #180, 1969 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Territorial integrity: statement of Eugene Pike, 1967 (Box-folder 3/21)
- National Rural Electric Co-Op Association, 1960-1976; Series VII; 0.5 linear feet
  Materials in this series were produced by the NRECA and include reports and workshop materials.
  Arranged alphabetically by genre, then chronologically.
  - Publication: Rural Electric Minuteman, 1963 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Report: Excess Earning and Your Light Bill, 1963 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Report: Irrigation study, 1969 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Report: Clean Air Act, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Report: Contribution to Electrical Power Research Institute, 1975 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Workshop: Workshop III, Developing a Better Understanding of Retail Electric Rates, 1959 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Workshop: Management Workshop V-B, 1960 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Workshop: Management Workshop V-I, 1960 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Workshop: Good for All Americans, 1963 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Workshop: Legal Seminar III, 1963 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Workshop: Suggested Plan of Training Programs, 1965 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Workshop: Good for All Americans II, 1965 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Workshop: Good for All Americans II, 1966 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Workshop: Legal Seminar XI, 1971 (Box-folder 4/8)
- U. S. Department of Agriculture, Rural Electric Administration, 1951-1959; Series VIII; 1 folder
  Consists of training materials made available to co-ops like the MEC.
  - Training materials, 1951-1959 and undated (Box-folder 4/9)
- Montana Associated Utilities, 1962-1976; Series IX; 4 folders
  Consists of reports, policy manuals, newsletter, and records of meetings.
  - Advertising Committee Report, 1968 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Board of Directors, regular and committee meetings, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - District meetings, 1969 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Newsletter, 1966 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Publication committee financial information, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Policy manual and report, 1962 and 1976 (Box-folder 5/6)
- Bonneville Power Company, 1963-1976; Series X; 0.25 linear feet
  This series contains financial and legal information, numerous publications, reports, and speeches.
  - Financial information and schedules, 1970-1973 and undated (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Legal, Contracts, WPPSS, 1972 and 1975 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Legal, Contracts, Department of the Interior, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Legal, Contract, Grays Harbor Nuclear Project, 1970 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Legal, 1974-1975 and undated (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Minutes, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Publications, "Fact Sheets", 1972-1976 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Publications, Pacific Northwest Power Transmission Map, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Reports, Appaloosa Dam Project, 1968 and undated (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Reports, 1963-1974 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Reports, generation and sales statistics, 1967 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Reports, generation and sales statistics, 1974 (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Reports, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 5/19)
  - Reports, purchase proposal, 1976 (Box-folder 5/20)
  - Reports, Ten-Year Hydro-Thermal Power Program for the Pacific Northwest, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5/21)
  - Speeches, 1962-1976 (Box-folder 5/22)
- Breeder Reactor Corporation, 1971-1976; Series XI; 0.25 linear feet
  These materials are largely reports concerning the construction and feasibility of breeder reactors, but also include some legal agreements.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - 1973-1975 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Legal, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Legal, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Publications, undated (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Report, An Introduction to the Breeder Reactor, 1972 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Report, Background of AEC Development, 1972 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Report, Liquid Metal Fast Breeder Reactor Project, 1972 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Report, Testimony Concerning the Liquid Metal Fast Breeder Reactor, undated (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Speech, Nuclear Power Considerations and Breeder Reactor, 1971 and undated (Box-folder 6/9)
- Northwest Intertie, 1963-1975; Series XII; 0.25 linear feet
  This series consists of materials from Northwest Intertie, an organization in which the MEC was apparently involved. Contents include records of meetings, articles of incorporation, and reports.
  Arranged chronologically by type of material.
  - Articles of Incorporation, Amendments, By-Laws, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Financial statements, 1964 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Financial statements, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Financial outlook, 1975 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Meetings, Public Power Council, 1966 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Meeting programs and agendas, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Minutes, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 6/16)
  - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Report, Pacific Northwest-Southwest intertie, 1964 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Report, Rate review, undated (Box-folder 6/19)
- Washington Public Power Supply System, 1962-1977; Series XIII; 1.0 linear foot
  This series contains extensive information on the WPPSS, particularly on its Hanford-area operations in southeastern Washington state and on its dealings with the Bonneville Power Administration. Includes reports, financial information, legal agreements.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of document, then chronologically.
  - Correspondence and memos, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 6/20)
  - Press releases, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 6/21)
  - Financial statements, Hanford, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 6/22)
  - Financial, balance sheets, Hanford, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 6/23)
  - Financial, balance sheets, Hanford, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Financial, balance sheets, Hanford, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Financial, future generating facility, 1976 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Financial, Hanford, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Financial, net billing analysis, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Financial, Hanford operating budget, 1976 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Financial, Hanford, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Financial, Hanford operating budget, 1973 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Financial, Hanford operating budget, 1974 (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Legal, contract 1962 (Box-folder 7/10)
  - Legal, Bonneville/WPPSS, 1962 (Box-folder 7/11)
  - Legal, agreement between WPPSS/Bonneville, 1973 (Box-folder 7/12)
  - Legal, agreements Hanford, 1974 (Box-folder 7/13)
  - Legal, agreements for projects #4 and #5 and Skagit project, 1975 (Box-folder 7/14)
  - Legal, Hanford, 1962 (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Legal, resolutions, 1970 (Box-folder 7/16)
  - Legal, resolution revenue bonds, 1973 (Box-folder 7/17)
  - Legal, resolutions, 1975 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Minutes, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Publications, Hanford History and Q & A, 1962-1974 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Publications, Information Kit, 1977 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Reports, Hanford, 1966-1976 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Reports, status, 1974 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Reports, status, 1974 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Reports, status, 1975 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Reports, status, 1975 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Reports, status, 1976 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Reports, status, 1977 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Reports, status, 1978 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Reports, supply system activities reports, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Reports, nuclear project construction cost summary reports, 1976 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Reports, Regional hydro-thermal Power integration, 1968 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Reports, report to participants, 1975 (Box-folder 9/8)
- Public Power Council, 1966-1976; Series XIV; 0.5 linear foot
  This series consists largely of meeting minutes from the PPC, but also includes legal materials and reports.
  - Financial, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Legal, resolutions, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Membership lists, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box-folder 9/13)
  - Minutes, 1972 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Minutes, 1973 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Minutes, 1976 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Policy statements, 1971 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Reports, 1966-1974 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Report, Review of Power Planning in the Pacific Northwest, 1972 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Speeches, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 10/8)
- Federal Power Commission, 1963 and 1975; Series XV; 2 folders
  This series contains legal materials and a report from the Federal Power Commission.
  - Legal, Department of Interior/Bonneville Power Administration, 1975 (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Report, List of Power Suppliers, 1963 (Box-folder 10/10)
- Northwest Public Power Association, 1968-1976; Series XVI; 5 folders
  This series contains meeting records, reports, and a speech associated with the NPPA.
  Arranged alphabetically by document type.
  - Legal, resolutions, 1970 and undated (Box-folder 10/11)
  - Minutes, board of trustees meetings, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 10/12)
  - Newsletters, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 10/13)
  - Report, consumer power policy, undated (Box-folder 10/14)
  - Reports, proposals, 1968 and undated (Box-folder 10/15)
  - Speeches, Henry Curtis, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 10/16)
- Montana Power Company, 1957-1966; Series XVII; 2 folders
  This series contains two reports from the MPC, on rates and its annual statistical report.
  - Reports, annual statistical report, 1957-1966 (Box-folder 10/17)
  - Reports, rates, 1950-1965 (Box-folder 10/18)
- Montana State Rural Electric Co-Op Association, 1958-1975; Series XVIII; 1 folder
  Consists of the Montana Rural Electric News 1958-1975.
  - Publication, Montana Rural Electric News, 1958-1975 (Box-folder 10/19)
- Other Groups, 1962-1979; Series XIX; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contains materials from the Columbia Storage Power Exchange, the Committee for Paradise Dam, the Edison Electric Institute, the Mecklenberg Electric Cooperative, member services, Oregonians for Nuclear Safeguards, the State of Montana, Washington State University, and Westinghouse. The Washington State University materials are concerned with the Power Professorship and with a program for students in which the MEC provided some internship opportunities. There is also a Reports and Rate schedule.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Columbia Storage Power Exchange, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Committee for Paradise Dam, 1962 and undated (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Edison Electric Institute, 1973 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Mecklenberg Electric Cooperative, member services, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Oregonians for Nuclear Safeguards, ca. 1974 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - State of Montana, Minimum Safety Standards for Powerline Construction in Montana, 1970 (Box-folder 11/6)
  - State of Montana, environmental impact statement for Missoula and Hamilton transmission line, 1972 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Washington State University, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Westinghouse, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 11/9)
  - Reports and Rate schedules, 1965-1971 and undated (Box-folder 11/10)